Date: Monday 18th May 2009

Time: 15:00-16:00 (UK)

Telcon No: 08445805588

Pin: 70503011

Attending

Manchester: Jits, Franck, Steve

EBI: Eric, Thomas, Rodrigo

Apologies

Carole

Minuting

Franck

Agenda

Actions from the last telcon

Update on EMBRACE work, post AGM - SRP

Hackathon summary

Annotation model document

Progress/developement of the pilot - are we rolling?

Report back from silent public release

Test infrastructure setup at EBI and progress of service testing/monitoring piece.

Technical meeting

Summary of tasks on Rubyforge

BioCatalogue support review

20 Questions analysis

Actions from Previous Meeting

Eric: provide an update on what is happening with the test scripts execution environment. completed

Franck & Eric : Produce elaborate document on the BioCatalogue data model - ongoing

Franck: identify all the non-bio service form the seekDa import - ongoing

Minutes

Update on EMBRACE work, post AGM - SRP

The Embrace registry has achieved its goals so can now be merged to BioCatalogue. The project will be supported till summer

Hackathon summary

All went down well. Eric to look into the workflow monitor with Dan. BioCatalogue and myExperiment integration scheduled for August.

Annotation model document

Still ongoing. there are some comments in the document to address. A new logial view of the model also needed

Progress/developement of the beta - are we rolling?

Test infrastructure setup at EBI and progress of service testing/monitoring piece. Ebi agreed to have the tests script provided we take responsibility by manually checking and monitoring all the scripts.

New actions

Rodrigo: find out with Peter Rice what the Biosapien ontology. Anything we can learn from?

Steve: Check if it is possible to come up with a classification from the Embrace registry tags

Upcoming Meetings

ISMB launch strategy: before the conference we should announce that we are launching BioCatalogue at ISMB.
Ebi will target a number of list: EMBnet, bionet, admins, etc…
Manchester will also target list such myExperiment mailing list, Taverna list etc…
Item to take to the conference: leaflet, poster, sticker, t-shirt(if possible).

AOB

Previous/Next Meetings

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Apr 27 2009

Next meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on June 06 2009

The BioCatalogue Core Team

Carole Goble: Project lead, Manchester

Rodrigo Lopez: Project lead, EBI

Steve Pettifer: Project lead, Manchester

Robert Stevens: Project lead, Manchester

Jiten Bhagat: Software engineer, Manchester

Robert Haines: Software engineer, Manchester

Hamish McWilliam: Service manager, EBI

Katy Wolstencroft: Bioinformatician, Manchester

Past Team Members

Franck Tanoh: Bioinformatician and curator, Manchester

Eric Nzuobontane: Software engineer, EBI

Thomas Laurent: Software engineer, EBI

Mannie Tagarira: Intern software engineer, Manchester

Sergejs Aleksevejs: Intern software engineer, Manchester

The Focus Group

See: the Focus Group page

Our Advisory Board

The BioCatalogue Strategic Advisory Board (SAB) members:

Dr Robert Stevens, School of Computer Science, University of Manchester, UK

Professor Chris Rawlings, Rothamsted Research, UK, Bioinformatics.

Professor Anil Wipat, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK, Bioinformatics.

Dr Jo Dicks, John Innes Centre, UK, Computational and Systems Biology.

Dr Robert Gill, Pronota nv, Belgium, Director of Bio-IT, previously at GSK.

Professor Steve Kemp, University of Liverpool, UK, Biology.

Dr Mark Wilkinson, U British Columbia, Canada, Bioinformatics, BioMOBY services.

Prof dr Antoine H.C. van Kampen, Netherlands Bioinformatics Centre, Scientific Director, Bioinformatics.

Holger Lausen, SeekDa OG, Austria, Web Service Search company, CTO and Co-Founder of web service discovery and matchmaking company.

Dr Terry Payne, University of Liverpool, UK, Computer Science, specialising in Semantic Web Services.

Installing and Running the BioCatalogue

This page describes how to download, set up and run the BioCatalogue system on your own machine(s).

Note: if you are setting up a development environment and working on the BioCatalogue codebase please also see the Codebase Guidelines.

Getting Help

For any assistance please join the biocatalogue-hackers mailing list and post your questions/feedback. Alternatively you can contact us directly at contact@biocatalogue.org.

General Requirements

*nix based system (not fully tested on MS Windows yet)

Subversion v1.6+

Ruby v1.8.5, v1.8.6 or v1.8.7

RubyGems v1.4 (> v1.4.2 not supported)

Oracle/Sun Java v1.6+

MySQL database v5.0+

Prerequisites

Ubuntu 10.04

NOTES

The instructions below assume you have the following package repos enabled and have all your packages up to date:

Canonical supported Open Source software (main)

Community maintained Open Source software (universe)

Software restricted by copyright or legal issues (multiverse)

Partner repository (for Java)

Ubuntu 10.04 has Ruby 1.8.7 as it's default Ruby package. The BioCatalogue software has not been thoroughly tested with this version of Ruby but “should just work”. If you encounter any issues with this set up please contact us.

Do not install the RubyGems package that comes by default. Manual installation instructions for the required RubyGems are described below.

Install Ruby, Java, MySQL, memcached and other packages required

sudo apt-get install subversion build-essential curl ruby rdoc irb ruby-dev libreadline-ruby1.8 libruby1.8 libopenssl-ruby libmysql-ruby libmysqlclient-dev zlib1g zlib1g-dev libxml2 libxml2-dev libxslt-dev libssl-dev sun-java6-jdk mysql-server memcached

Setup Oracle/Sun Java to be the default

sudo update-java-alternatives -s java-6-sun
java -version

Install RubyGems

Please note: currently, due to breaking changes, RubyGems versions greater than 1.4.2 WILL NOT work.

cd /tmp
wget http://production.cf.rubygems.org/rubygems/rubygems-1.4.2.tgz
tar zfxv rubygems-1.4.2.tgz
cd rubygems-1.4.2/
sudo ruby ./setup.rb
cd /usr/bin/
sudo ln -s gem1.8 gem

Start up the required services (if required)

sudo service memcached start
sudo service mysql start

Debian 5

NOTES

The instructions below assume you have the following package repos enabled and have all your packages up to date:

“Officially supported (main)”

“DFSG-compatible Software with Non-Free Dependencies (contrib)”

“Non-DFSG-compatible Software (non-Free)”

Debian 5 has Ruby 1.8.7 as it's default Ruby package. The BioCatalogue software has not been thoroughly tested with this version of Ruby but “should just work”. If you encounter any issues with this set up please contact us.

Do not install the RubyGems package that comes by default. Manual installation instructions for the required RubyGems are described below.

Install Ruby, Java, MySQL, memcached and other packages required

sudo apt-get install subversion ruby rdoc ri irb libopenssl-ruby ruby-dev mysql-server libssl-dev libmysqlclient15-dev libmagick++9-dev build-essential curl libxml++2.6-dev sun-java6-jdk memcached

Setup Oracle/Sun Java to be the default

sudo update-java-alternatives -s java-6-sun
java -version

Install RubyGems

Please note: currently, due to breaking changes, RubyGems versions greater than 1.4.2 WILL NOT work.

cd /tmp
wget http://production.cf.rubygems.org/rubygems/rubygems-1.4.2.tgz
tar zfxv rubygems-1.4.2.tgz
cd rubygems-1.4.2/
sudo ruby ./setup.rb
cd /usr/bin/
sudo ln -s gem1.8 gem
cd -

Start up the required services (if required)

sudo /etc/init.d/memcached start
sudo /etc/init.d/mysql start

Mac OS X 10.6 Snow Leopard

NOTES

The instructions below assume you have the following installed on your system:

Xcode Tools (available from Apple [1]

A 64 bit version of MySQL 5.1.x (available from [2]). Please note that your Mac needs to be running in 64 bit mode as well; the 32 bit config has not been tested yet.

Do not use the Ruby and RubyGems packages that comes by default. Manual installation instructions are described below.

Before installing any of the packages, the following line needs to be added to the end of your ~/.profile file:

export PATH="/usr/local/bin:/usr/local/sbin:/usr/local/mysql/bin:$PATH"

Install Ruby

cd /tmp
curl -O ftp://ftp.ruby-lang.org/pub/ruby/1.8/ruby-1.8.7-p174.tar.gz
tar xzvf ruby-1.8.7-p174.tar.gz
cd ruby-1.8.7-p174
./configure --enable-shared --enable-pthread CFLAGS=-D_XOPEN_SOURCE=1
make
sudo make install
cd -

Install RubyGems

Please note: currently, due to breaking changes, RubyGems versions greater than 1.4.2 WILL NOT work.

cd /tmp
curl -O http://files.rubyforge.vm.bytemark.co.uk/rubygems/rubygems-1.4.2.tgz
tar xzvf rubygems-1.4.2.tgz
cd rubygems-1.4.2
sudo /usr/local/bin/ruby setup.rb
cd -

Install MySQL Gem

sudo gem install mysql -- --with-mysql-dir=$(which mysql)

Start up the required services (if required)

sudo service memcached start
sudo service mysql start

Setting up the BioCatalogue System

NOTES

For production set ups always add RAILS_ENV=production to the end of the command (or add this as a global environment variable in your set up). For the server and console you can also do:

ruby script/server -e production

ruby script/console production

Install the required Ruby Gems

gem install solr-ruby dnsruby tzinfo
gem install libxml-ruby -v 1.1.4
gem install addressable -v 2.2.2
gem install daemons -v 1.1.3
gem install SystemTimer -v 1.2.3
gem install ZenTest -v 4.3.3
gem install RubyInline -v 3.8.6
gem install json -v 1.4.6
gem install mysql -v 2.8.1
gem install mongrel -v 1.1.5

Get the source code

In the folder you want BioCatalogue to be set up in, check out the source code:

cd ~
git clone https://github.com/myGrid/biocatalogue

Set up MySQL

In a MySQL shell do:

create database biocat_dev;
create database biocat_prod;
create database biocat_test;

Set up configurations and folders

Note: spaces and tabs are very important in .yml files. They must be used consistently.

In the application's directory:

Copy config/database.yml.pre to config/database.yml and configure accordingly (see file for more help)

Copy config/solr.yml.pre to config/solr.yml and configure accordingly (see file for more help)

Copy config/preinitializer.rb.pre to config/preinitializer.rb and configure accordingly (see file for more help)

Copy config/memcache.yml.pre to config/memcache.yml and configure accordingly. Example:

test:
  ttl: 604800
  sessions: false
  debug: false
  namespace: biocat_test
  servers: localhost:11211

development:
  ttl: 604800
  sessions: false
  debug: false
  namespace: biocat_dev
  servers: localhost:11211

production:
  ttl: 604800
  sessions: false
  debug: false
  namespace: biocat_prod
  servers: localhost:11211

Copy config/initializers/biocat_local.rb.pre to config/initializers/biocat_local.rb and configure accordingly

Copy config/initializers/mail.rb.pre to config/initializers/mail.rb and configure accordingly

Copy data/service_categories.yml.pre to data/service_categories.yml and configure your categories if required.

Copy public/stylesheets/colour-override.css.pre to public/stylesheets/colour-override.css and configure the main site colours as required.

Create some required folders. In the application's directory:

mkdir log tmp
cd tmp
mkdir cache pids sessions sockets

Set up the BioCatalogue database schema

First, temporarily set ENABLE_SEARCH to false in config/initializers/biocat_local.rb.

Then:

rake db:migrate

If that doesn't work, see the section Production Database.

Search server

The search server (Solr) is embedded within the application (for more info, see the section Search Server (Solr)).

To start the search server (in a separate terminal):

rake solr:start

To stop the search server:

rake solr:stop

Run the asset packager (for production mode only)

We have a mechanism to package up all CSS and JS files together to improve on performance. This works in (and is required for) production mode only.

rake asset:packager:build_all

WSDL Parsing Service

Set up the WSDL Parser Service by following the instructions in the README.txt.

You will then need to modify the relevant setting in config/initializers/biocat_local.rb.

Alternatively you can use the BioCatalogue test site one (not guaranteed to always be available):

WSDLUTILS_BASE_URI = 'http://test.biocatalogue.org/WSDLUtils/WSDLUtils.php'

Running the BioCatalogue System

To start up a server, in the application's directory (i.e. the “biocatalogue” directory):

ruby script/server

Then open up the web page at:

http://localhost:3000

Running the BioCatalogue Monitoring

Monitoring in BioCatalogue is done at two levels:

Availability monitoring, which is integrated with application

Functional monitoring, which is run as an external service

Availability Monitoring

The first step in setting this up is making sure that job workers are running as monitoring is done in a background process. Run the following:

 ruby script/worker start 

Note: By default, this runs the job workers in production mode.

Then run the following two rake tasks:

 rake biocatalogue:submit:update_urls_to_monitor  RAILS_ENV="your environment"
rake biocatalogue:submit:check_url_status RAILS_ENV="your environment"

That is it for the availability monitoring.

To run the monitoring on a regular basis, you could setup a cron job to run the two rake task given above

Functional Monitoring

Requires :

Python 2.5 or higher

This is done via test scripts. These can be either perl or python scripts or soapUI project files (xml). The package for running these is available in

 vendor/embrace_scripts 

The instructions for setting this up are available in the README file in that package

More Info

Adding an Initial Admin User

Run the application and sign up for a new user via the web interface.

Then, on the command line, start the Rails console in the application's directory (i.e. the “biocatalogue” directory):

ruby script/console production

And type the following:

u = User.first    # Assuming the user you signed up is the first one in the catalogue
u.activate!       # This activates the user
u.role_id = 1     # This makes the user an Admin
u.save!

Production Database

Before: temporarily set ENABLE_SEARCH to false in config/initializers/biocat_local.rb.

In order to create the production database you can do:

rake db:schema:load RAILS_ENV=production

This will load the schema up from /db/schema.rb (which should be kept up to date with the command “rake db:schema:dump”).

Then import the data (or use it empty).

NOTE: this does mean that the initial Registry entries for Feta and SeekDa will not be in there. We need a proper mechanism for importing initial data.

Search Server (Solr)

The solr service comes with the acts_as_solr plugin in our codebase so nothing has to be installed in order to have search enabled.

To start the search server open a command line in the root of the application and type:

rake solr:start

To stop the search server:

rake solr:stop

To reindex everything in the production database:

rake solr:reindex RAILS_ENV=production –trace

(make sure that the production solr instance has been started)

To reindex everything in the development database:

rake solr:reindex –trace

To optimise the production mode index:

ruby script/runner -e production "Service.solr_optimize"

To optimise the development mode index:

ruby script/runner "Service.solr_optimize"

[1] http://developer.apple.com

[2] http://dev.mysql.com/downloads/mysql